<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Considerations and exhortations to the serious and religious observation of the Lent-fast, enjoined by authority humbly proposed in tendency to promote a reformation of manners in the debauched age we live in / by P. A., Gent.</title>
            <author>P. A., Gent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A24695</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19145</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12603630</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12603630</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64239</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A24695)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64239)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 339:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Considerations and exhortations to the serious and religious observation of the Lent-fast, enjoined by authority humbly proposed in tendency to promote a reformation of manners in the debauched age we live in / by P. A., Gent.</title>
                  <author>P. A., Gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by John Nutt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fasts and feasts.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64239:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64239:1"/>
            <p>CONSIDERATIONS AND EXHORTATIONS TO THE Serious and Religious Obſervation OF THE <hi>Lent-Faſt,</hi> Enjoined by AUTHORITY. Humbly Propoſed in tendency to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote a Reformation of Manners in the Debauched Age we live in.</p>
            <p>By <hi>P. A.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paenitentia vera nunquam ſera.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. xxix. 1.</bibl> He that being often reproved, hardeneth his neck, ſhall ſuddenly be deſtroyed, and that without remedy.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed and are to be Sold by <hi>John Nutt,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:64239:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64239:2"/>
            <head>CONSIDERATIONS AND EXHORTATIONS TO THE Serious and Religious Obſervation OF THE LENT-FAST.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>BY way of PREFACE, you may pleaſe to take notice, That the following <hi>Eſſay</hi> is chiefly tranſcribed out of a larger Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the Author, printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1685, at the Death of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. then Dedicated to my Lord <hi>Dartmouth,</hi> Maſter of the Horſe to King <hi>James</hi> II. at his coming to the Crown. The Author humbly conceiving it may not be unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, now we are again entred upon the <hi>Lent-Faſt:</hi> For <hi>a word ſpoken in ſeaſon, how good is it?</hi> Prov. xv. 23. more-eſpecially this following his <hi>Chriſtian
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64239:3"/>Conſiderations for Chriſtmas</hi> paſt, as a ſecond ſtep made for the Reformation of Manners. For if People would be perſuaded religiouſly to obſerve the <hi>Lent-Fast,</hi> it might poſſibly prove a ſecond ſtep alſo towards the ſame good End: Provided alſo, that thoſe who are eminently engaged in the ſaid Noble Deſign, would be careful to be of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Converſation themſelves, that People may not have this to object truly, what is in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Porverb, <hi>That Vice corrects Sin.</hi> For this hath been found to be true, in all Ages of the World, <hi>Vivitur Exemplis magis quam Legibus,</hi> Men are led more by Example, than by Precept or by Laws.</p>
               <p>And may I, without offence, here mention that Teſtimony of Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> in his printed <hi>Travels into Italy,</hi> not long ſince, That in that great and populous City of <hi>Rome,</hi> when he was there, there was ſuch a wiſe Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity in the Government of it, that deſerved great Commendation; for that Publick Vices were not to be ſeen there. I heartily wiſh that it might be ſo ſaid of the City of <hi>London,</hi> who have doubtleſs a better Reformed Chriſtianity than they at <hi>Rome,</hi> to be the Foundation of it.</p>
               <p>And now I hope my enſuing Diſcourſe may prove more acceptable, my Deſign being for promoting ſo great a Good to us, as the compleating of our true Repentance, and the Safety of our Souls, that I have preſented what I have diſcourſed, in <hi>miniature,</hi> in little, being all circumſcribed within one Sheet of Paper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64239:3"/>
               <p>THAT a Religious <hi>Abſtinence</hi> and <hi>Faſting,</hi> in tendency to appeaſe God's Diſpleaſure againſt a Nation and People, and for the <hi>Reforming of Manners,</hi> was a Duty always acknowledged both by Jews and Chriſtians, in all Ages of the World; yea, what even Heathens and Mahometans have ſince conſented to.</p>
               <p>As to the Antiquity of the <hi>Lent-Fast,</hi> and the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of it (as a learned Man tells us) it is (like the River <hi>Nilus</hi>) we can ſcarce find out its Head, it being mention'd by <hi>Ignatius</hi> and <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> two of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Scholars; alſo by <hi>Origen,</hi> who lived not long after them; alſo in the famous Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> where they mention the Forty Days of <hi>Lent</hi> as a thing known and long obſerved before that time. How far our Bleſſed Saviour did approve of the Performance of this Chriſtian Duty, both by his Practice and Doctrine, is too evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to be denied. But certainly, if we had not the aforeſaid Evidence of the Sacred Scriptures and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, no Man of Reaſon and Conſcience, who believes he hath an Immortal Soul, capable of Eternal Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Miſery, Reward or Puniſhment, can doubt but that the Religious Obſervation of this Time of <hi>Lent,</hi> by Faſting, Abſtinence, and Self-denial, calling our ſelves to an Account of our Lives, ſerious Conſideration, and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, hath a wiſe and great tendency to the promoting of Piety and Vertue in us; (for, as one tells us, that, in truth, to a good Man, <hi>Vita est Reflectio.</hi>) And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be moſt wiſely recommended to our Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this Holy Time of <hi>Lent</hi>) in Commemoration of our Great Lord and Maſter, the Bleſſed Jeſus, his Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Forty Days and Forty Nights: Which Intention of the Church is fully expreſſed in her Collect for the Firſt <hi>Sunday</hi> in <hi>Lent, (viz.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord, who for our ſakes didst fast Forty Days, and Forty Nights, give us Grace to uſe ſuch Abſtinence, that our Fleſh being ſubdued to the Spirit, we may ever obey
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64239:4"/>thy Godly Motions, in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs to thy Honour and Glory,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And it is a thing acknowledged by all Men, That the grand Reaſon and Ground of the Prevalency of Vice and Wickedneſs in the World, is chiefly and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally from the want of ſober, ſerious and wiſe Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, (this being moſt true, That inconſiderate Men are wicked Men.) For Men are led by their ſenſual Appetites and Paſſions, which ſtick cloſe to them, and indeed are ſo great a part of themſelves, that it lays Reaſon, many times, aſleep. It much concerns us to exerciſe Reaſon, and ſerious Conſideration, as well as Faith: And it hath been found by Experience (that wiſe and great Inſtructor of Mankind) that the ſtrict and religious Obſervation of this Time of <hi>Lent,</hi> hath proved to be a mighty Reſtraint to Irreligion, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs, and Debauchery; yea, even in thoſe Places where Men are moſt exquiſite in Wickedneſs: That it hath been matter of Admiration and Wonder to Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers, to ſee ſuch a change of Manners, and what an Outward Appearance there is among them of Demure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Sobriety, Seriouſneſs and Devotion. I ſhall give it you in the words of that learned and excellent Perſon of our own Country, Sir <hi>Edwin Sandys,</hi> in his <hi>Europae Speculum,</hi> where, ſpeaking of <hi>Italy,</hi> he ſaith, That notwithſtanding the abounding of Vice among them, yet during the Time of <hi>Lent,</hi> the People of all ſorts are then much reformed; no ſuch Blaſphemy nor dirty Speaking as before; their Vanity of all ſorts laid reaſonably aſide, their Pleaſures abandon'd, their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, their Diet, and all things elſe, compoſed to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, and a ſtate of Penitence; they have daily then their Preaching, with Collections of Alms, whereto all Men reſort; and to judge of them by their outward ſhew, they ſeem generally to have very great Remorſe for their Wickedneſs; inſomuch (ſaith he) as I muſt confeſs, I ſeemed unto my ſelf in <hi>Italy</hi> to have beſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64239:4"/>learn'd the right Uſe of <hi>Lent,</hi> and there firſt to have diſcerned the great fruit of it, and the Reaſon for which thoſe Sages in the Church at firſt did inſtitute it. Neither can I (ſaith he) eaſily accord to the Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of ſuch, as becauſe we ought at all times to lead a life worthy of our Profeſſion, that therefore it is Superſtitious to have any Time wherein to exert or expect it more than other; but do thus rather conceive, that the Corruption of Times, and the Wickedneſs of Man's Nature, is ſo exorbitant, that it was a hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to hold the ordinary ſort of Men, at all times, within the Liſts of Piety, Juſtice and Sobriety: It is fit therefore that there ſhould be one time, at leaſt, in the Year, and that of a reaſonable continuance, according to the Practice of all Men, (for even the Jews and Turks have their <hi>Lents</hi>) to conſtrain Men, how wicked and wretchleſs ſoever, for that time at leaſt, to recall them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſome more ſevere Cogitations and Courſes, leſt Sin having no ſuch Bridle to check it at any time, ſhould at length become head-ſtrong and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querable in them; as alſo to enure Men (though but to a bare ſhew of Vertue) they might afterwards, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, more ſeriouſly perſiſt in it.— By this we underſtand the manner of keeping <hi>Lent</hi> among the Romaniſts beyond Seas, eſpecially in <hi>Italy,</hi> with the worthy Perſon the Author's judicious Comment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon.</p>
               <p>Now ſurely (I humbly conceive) have we not here, in <hi>England,</hi> as great Reaſon to be ſtrict Obſervers of this Holy Time of <hi>Lent,</hi> as Foreigners? For is it not too apparent, that Irreligion, Vice, Debauchery and Wickedneſs encreaſeth and grows upon us, and that it has need of Reſtraints to be put upon it, leſt it ſwallow us up? And therefore (I humbly conceive) it much concerns us, inſtead of rejecting, and laying aſide, and prophanely ſcoffing at the ſtrict and religious Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of this ſolemn Time of <hi>Lent</hi> among the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64239:5"/>rather to learn that which is good and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in our Adverſaries. For ſhall it be ſaid, that when the whole Chriſtian World are ſober and ſerious, in keeping their <hi>Lent-Fast,</hi> and humbling their Souls, in conſideration of their great Sins and Provocations of the Divine Majeſty of Heaven, and ſpend their Time in Self-denials, and Mortifications, and are upon their Knees humbling their Souls, and with fervent and frequent Prayers interceding with to God for Mercy, that we in <hi>England</hi> (who would be accounted better, and Reformed Chriſtians) are, inſtead thereof, taken up with our Feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Jollities, if not our Debauches and Exceſſes, and have ſo little ſenſe of our great Tranſgreſſions and Provocations of God, as to be ſo far diſpleaſed with our ſelves for the ſame, as to deny our ſelves now and then a Meal's Meat, or at leaſt ſomewhat of our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, or from our more pleaſant Food, or from taking a revenge upon our ſelves, by our Abſtinence, for our great Sins and Tranſgreſſions, and from ſpending our Time in ſober and ſerious Conſideration of our Ways and Doings, and the ſtate of our Souls; and further, by Faſting, adding Force to our Prayers to God for Mercy to our ſelves and others, the whole Church and Nation wherein we live; and Praying mightily to God, that ſo our Sins may not out-cry our Prayers?</p>
               <p>Let us further conſider, that this Outward Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance and Face of Religion and Devotion, (although it be but for a time) yet what effect it may have upon Men, we know not; but that it may make ſome Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion on Mens Minds, as to fall in love and liking of ſincere and true Piety, ſo that it may in time prevail upon them to become honeſt and ſincere; and not only lay aſide their Folly and Wickedneſs for a ſeaſon, but wholly abandon their Luſts: For this Reſtraint they put upon themſelves for a ſeaſon, muſt mightily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them that they have power over themſelves to reſtrain their diſorder'd and vitious Appetites and Luſts
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64239:5"/>for a time; and why not then longer, if they pleaſe? It will ſomewhat inure and accuſtom them to Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial, and Mortification of their Senſual Appetites. And they who deny themſelves, if it be only but for a time, will be accounted, however, leſs wicked than thoſe who will abate nothing of their Wickedneſs and Exceſſes at any time, nor apply themſelves to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Duties of the <hi>Lent-Fast;</hi> eſpecially if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how far even a formal and hypocritical Faſt and Humiliation for a time of a wicked <hi>Ahab</hi> had accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance before God, as to his Deliverance from a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Judgment, during his Life.</p>
               <p>Let us conſider the great Wiſdom of the Church, our Mother, in appointing this <hi>Lent-Fast;</hi> which, if not impoſed upon her Children, they (it's to be feared) would very careleſsly and ſlightly paſs over the ſerious Duties of this Time, and poſſibly never find a ſeaſon for this neceſſary Work of a Chriſtian, of conſidering their Ways, and ſearching their Hearts, and repenting and humbling themſelves, and pouring out their fervent Prayers for God's Pardon, and for the Almighty Aſſiſtance of his Grace and Spirit to aſſiſt them in their honeſt Endeavours, as alſo of conſulting a good Spiritual Guide and Director of their Souls (moſt ſeaſonable at this ſerious Time to moſt People) from whom they may receive ghoſtly Advice and Counſel how to avoid the Temptations and Occaſions of Sin for the future, and how to make Satisfaction for Injuries done by them to their Neighbours, and how to frame ſuch holy Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Amendment of their Lives as may prove effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual; as alſo to have further the Determination of a faithful and able Guide to determine for them of their own Sincerity, and as to the true ſtate of their Souls, (who are, God knows, too ready to judge too favourably of themſelves.) For this Time of <hi>Lent</hi> may be not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly conſidered as a time of entrance into a Courſe of Phyſick for our Souls Health and Safety. And why
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64239:6"/>may not it be as neceſſary, in point of Prudence and Safety, to procure, and often to conſult an able Divine, for our Souls Health and Welfare, as it is to conſult an able Phyſician for the Health of the Body, or an able Lawyer for the Safety and Security of our Eſtate? I can ſee no difference, except it be this, that we think the Concerns of our Souls are leaſt worth our Regard and Care; that any bold Mountebank and unskilful Pretender, may ſerve the turn. But without all doubt, to make our Repentance true and effectual, to make our Peace with God, to obtain a wiſe and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſtructed Mind and Conſcience in the Affairs of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, thereby to poſſeſs a ſpotleſs and innocent Soul, a good Conſcience, an unprejudiced Mind and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in Religion, and the true Fear and Love of God, are doubtleſs the greateſt and richeſt Happineſſes of Humane Life, and will be moſt certainly introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to Eternal Happineſs, which is inſured to us by the Satisfaction and Redemption purchaſed for us by the precious Blood of our Great Saviour and Redeemer, Jeſus Chriſt, to all ſincere Chriſtians who neglect not the Means to attain it.</p>
               <p>Let us (as is before mention'd) conſider, that for our Spiritual Improvement and Welfare, this holy Time of <hi>Lent</hi> was inſtituted by the Ancient Chriſtian Church (long before Popery appeared in the World:) I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly therefore conceive it would be a great weakneſs and folly of us Proteſtants to diſcard it for Popiſh and Superſtitious; but rather heartily embrace it, and to endeavour to make thoſe great Advantages to our Souls, by the Primitive Religious Obſervance of it. For ſurely the more and better Reformed our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is that we profeſs to own, it ſhould make us the more to love God, and our Neighbour, and to have a greater Fervency and Zeal for all Chriſtian Duties, eſpecially thoſe of this Time of <hi>Lent;</hi> and herein to exceed our Adverſaries, the Romaniſts; for elſe they,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64239:6"/>with their more corrupted Chriſtianity, will condemn us for our Abuſe of our better Chriſtianity we enjoy.</p>
               <p>Now let us ſay to our ſelves, every one of us, O what a bleſſed and hapyy Advantage have I, by this Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity now offer'd unto me by the Care of my Indulgent Mother, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in appointing and conſtituting this Holy Faſt of <hi>Lent,</hi> for the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Examination of my Heart, and all my Ways, repenting of, and confeſſing my Sins, and obtaining Pardon for them, and making of my Peace with God, of renewing my Vows and Reſolutions of Amendment, of pouring forth my fervent and frequent Prayers, and therein may endeavour after the mortifying my Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions Appetites and Luſts, of quickening my Graces, of conſulting a Spiritual Guide of my Soul, and that I may be conformed to the Image of the Bleſſed Jeſus in Holineſs, and thereby to be inſured of my Eternal Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, by participating of the Holy Sacrament of his Body and Blood, at the end of this Holy <hi>Faſt.</hi> How unworthy ſhall I be, if I neglect to perform thoſe Chriſtian Duties required of me? I will not ſlight or neglect them: I will religiouſly ſpend my Time in dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Examination of all my Sins, repenting of them, confeſſing and bewailing them, and ſo make my firm Reſolutions of Amendment; I will certainly caſt them off with abhorrence and deteſtation; I will be ſerious and wiſe; I will Faſt, and learn now to deny my ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Appetites and Luſts, and then pray earneſtly to God for his Grace and Spirit, which he hath promiſed to them that earneſtly beg it of him, to enable me in my Chriſtian Combat againſt all my Enemies, the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil; I will diſpenſe my Alms liberally, according to my Ability; I will uſe my utmoſt endeavour to lay a Foundation in my Soul of the Fear and Love of God, of ſolid Peace to my Soul, and Mind, and Conſcience, of ſincere Piety and Vertue: And by this means making this Holy Time of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64239:7"/>
                  <hi>Lent,</hi> a time of Traffick for my Souls Concerns and Neceſſities; and thus anſwering the End of this Holy <hi>Fast,</hi> for which it was deſign'd by the Church, and then ply my Devotions, and make uſe, among others, of that Prayer of a worthy Divine, moſt excellent and comprehenſive, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>GRant me, most merciful God, a fervent Zeal, to deſire ſuch things as are moſt acceptable to thee, and a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diligence to ſearch after them; give me wiſdom to find them, and thy grace to accompliſh them, to the praiſe and glory of thy holy Name. Direct thou my Life, that I may have both knowledge, will and power always to do that which is most pleaſing to thee, and most expedient for my own ſoul. Let my way to thee, O Lord, be ſure, ſtreight and perfect, that neither adverſity nor proſperity make me fall away from thee; that I be not puft up with pride with the one, nor driven down into deſpair with the other, but for the one give thanks, and be with the other armed with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience; that I may rejoyce in nothing but that which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proacheth near to thee, my bleſſed Jeſus, nor ſorry for any thing but that which withdraweth me from thee; that I deſire to pleaſe or diſpleaſe none but thee, and for thee; that all tranſitory things may, for thy ſake, be of no reputation with me, and whatſoever is agreeable to thy will, may be delightful to mine, and thou my God above all things; that I may have no joy beſides thee, nor deſireof any thing but thee. Let all labour delight me that is taken for thee, and all eaſe be unpleaſant that is without thee; make me lift up my heart often to thee; and when I forget thee, give me grace to call to mind my ſins with ſorrow, and full purpoſe of amendment. Grant that I may be obedient with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contradiction, patient without murmuring, pure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out corruption, humble without counterfeiting, chearful without levity, ſad without dejection, true without double<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, fearing thee without deſpair: To do good works, but not to preſume, telling my neighbour his fault without flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, inſtructing him both by word and example without
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64239:7"/>ſcorning or taunting. Grant me, moſt loving Lord, a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful mind which no worldly thought may divert from thee, a conſtant ſpirit which no evil affection or wicked ſuggeſtion may withdraw from thee, a heart ſo ſtable that no trouble may overcome me, and ſo free from vice that ſin may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge no place in me. Grant me, O Lord, underſtanding to know thee, wiſdom to find thee, converſation to pleaſe thee, that I may faithfully perſevere in loving thee to the end, and finally ever enjoy thee. And in reſpect of thy moſt grievous Pains ſuffered upon the Croſs for me, that I may willingly ſuffer penance, and all tribulation for thee. Give me, O Lord, thy grace in this tranſitory life, and in the world to come make me partaker of the reward, and heavenly joy, through the precious Blood of that Immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Lamb our only Saviour and Redeemer, Jeſus Chriſt; To whom, with the Father and the Holy Ghost, Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and One God, be all Honour and glory, World with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>And conſidering we live in an Age, <hi>that the World is become ſo much Knave</hi> (as one ſpeaks) <hi>that it is a Crime to be Honest,</hi> (although the wiſe Heathens accounted Honeſty the greateſt Good, and the only Good) and that Truth and Honeſty ſeems to be fled to Heaven, and that Intereſt and Profit governs all; let us not forget, in our Prayers, earneſtly to beg of God that they may return among us, and that Old <hi>England</hi>'s Honeſty may come once again in repute among us, which cauſed Men to think that <hi>Sola honeſta utilia, i. e.</hi> That only honeſt things are profitable. So that one Ounce of Honeſty was of more worth than a Pound of Cunning: And let us cry out with that wiſe Heathen, <hi>Seneca, O quantum mali est nimium ſubtilitatis!</hi> O what a great miſchief is too much Cunning!</p>
               <p>And may I make this further Addition to the former Diſcourſe, being very pertinent to it, and what a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Author diſcourſes to us, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That the great Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and of our coming into the World, is but to prepare
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64239:8"/>our ſelves for a better; and that all the Buſineſs of a Pariſh Prieſt or Miniſter is not confined to the Pulpit, but that there is other Buſineſs (if the People would think of it) wherein to employ Men of that Profeſſion. To tell you what I mean (ſaith he) not in mine own, but his expreſſions who knew better what belong'd to the Court of Conſcience, (meaning the worthy Prelate, Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi>) who, in his Eighth Sermon of <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Faſting,</hi> ſaith, I take it to be a great Error to think the Fruits of Repentance, and the worth of them, to be a matter any common Man can skill of well enough, needs never ask St. <hi>John</hi> or St. <hi>Paul</hi> what he ſhould do, but knows what he ſhould do as well as St. <hi>Paul</hi> or St. <hi>John</hi> either; and that it is not rather a matter wherein we need the Counſel and Direction of ſuch as are profeſſed that way: Truly, it is neither the leaſt nor the laſt part of our Learning to be able to give an Anſwer and Direction in this Point; but therefore laid aſide and neglected by us, becauſe not ſought after by you, and therefore not ſtudied but by very few; becauſe, <hi>Nemo nos Interrogat,</hi> (i. e.) No body asks us the Queſtion; becauſe it grows quite out of requeſt.</p>
               <p>We have learned, I know not where, a new and ſhorter courſe, which Fleſh and Blood better like of, <hi>viz.</hi> in the whole courſe of our Life, not to be able to ſet down where, or when, or what we did; when we did that which we call Repenting, and what Fruits there came of it; what thoſe Fruits might be worth; but even a little before death (and that as little as may be) not till the World hath given us over: Lo then, to come to our <hi>Quid faciemus,</hi> (i. e.) to ask what ſhall we do, when we are able to do nothing; and then one muſt come, and (as we call it) ſpeak comfortably to us, that is to ſay, miniſter unto us a little Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity <hi>Laudanum,</hi> rather ſtupefactive for the preſent, than doing any ſound good, and ſo take our leaves, to go meet with <hi>Ira ventura,</hi> (i. e.) the Wrath to come
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64239:8"/>This way, this faſhion of Repenting, St. <hi>John</hi> knew it not, it is far from his <hi>Fructus dignus,</hi> (i. e.) worthy Fruit. St. <hi>Paul</hi> knew it not, it is far from his <hi>Opera digna,</hi> (i. e.) worthy Works: And I can ſay little to it, but I pray God it do not deceive us; for it is not good trying Concluſions about our Souls.</p>
               <p>Now, ſaith the Author, This excellent Diſcourſe is ſo fair an <hi>Item</hi> to a tender, pious Chriſtian, from diverting him, and thereby deferring the making of his Accounts even with Heaven, till the Croſs or Bed of Sickneſs call upon him; ſure, that's no Time or Place to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt with two ſuch Enemies as Infirmity of Bodies, and of Sins. Unto which another worthy Author adds his Advice, which is, To renounce the Errors and Neglects of the Age we live in, and imitate the Piety of thoſe Chriſtians who lived in the firſt Ages of the Chriſtian Church, if we will fight well in our Chriſtian Combat.</p>
               <p>And indeed, the Truth of our Repentance is our All; for, as it hath been ſaid, we muſt have Innocency, or true Repentance, to make us acceptable to God. As for the firſt, no Man hath it, and therefore we muſt truſt wholly upon the latter.</p>
               <p>I need ſay no more of this Subject of Repentance, but to adviſe us all to hearken diligently to what our Mother the Church ſpeaketh to us, and adviſeth in her Excellent <hi>Liturgy</hi> for this Time of <hi>Lent.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>
               <hi>An</hi> APPENDIX <hi>to the preceding Diſcourſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN my <hi>Eſſay for the Promoting the Religious Obſervation of the Faſt-Day,</hi> January <hi>the</hi> 30th, laſt paſt (being ſtreightned in Time) I could not then fully expreſs my Thoughts, and have therefore annex'd them here, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That in truth, King <hi>Charles</hi> I. his greateſt Crime was, his managing a War againſt his Rebellious Subjects, to uphold the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and maintain Epiſcopacy, according to his Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation Oa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h; and accordingly I have heard even that great Presbyterian Divine, Doctor <hi>Cornelius Burgeſs</hi> in thoſe times, in his Pulpit, term that Civil War, <hi>Bellam Epiſcopale,</hi> the Epiſcopal War, which it truly was.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64239:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And may I recommend to the peruſal of all ingenuous Perſons, that excellent Printed Sermon of Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> (now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi>) which he preach'd at the <hi>Savoy</hi> Church, <hi>January</hi> 30. <hi>Anno</hi> 1674. wherein they will find a ſufficient Proof of the great Abilities of Mind of the Royal Martyr, King <hi>Charles</hi> I. To which if they pleaſe to add his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation at <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> with Mr. <hi>Henderſon,</hi> as alſo his managing the Perſonal Treaty at <hi>Newport,</hi> in the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> Anno 1648. they may be fully ſatisfy'd of the little need he had of Dr. <hi>Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi>'s (or Dr. <hi>Bailey</hi>'s Aſſiſtance, who was alſo ſaid to be the Compiler of the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Book</hi> in former times) and how then, at laſt, it ſhould fall upon Dr. <hi>Gauden,</hi> I cannot imagine, when he had no need of any one to aſſiſt him, and more eſpecially of Dr. <hi>Gauden,</hi> who had taken the Covenant, (as is affirmed, and was alſo a Stranger to him) when it is well known the ſaid Prince had ſuch an Antipathy againſt ſuch as had taken the Covenant, that he could not be perſuaded, at the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> ſo much as to hear one of thoſe Presbyterian Divines that attended the Parliaments Commiſſioners there, to Preach before him, although very great and celebrated Preachers, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Marſhall, Mr. Vines,</hi> Mr. <hi>Caryll,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Seaman;</hi> and he never, all the time of the Treaty, went to Church, but heard his own Biſhops and Doctors, who preach'd to him in the <hi>Preſence-Chamber;</hi> all which I my ſelf knew very well, who was there all the Time of the ſaid Treaty, and ſome Days after it ended. Which, I humbly conceive, makes it incredible that the King ſhould admit of Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> to be a Guide of his Conſcience. But to ſay no more, but to end this Controverſie, What can be the meaning of the great Buſtle about it, and thoſe concerned therein, except it be to blacken the Royal Martyr, and his Sacred Memory, that they may whiten <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> and the reſt of the wicked Regicides; which, if ſo, let them take the glory of it to themſelves, who delight in it: God grant that all good and honeſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians may be free from having a Hand in the ſame: For <hi>he that juſtifieth the wicked, and he that condemneth the just, even they both are abomination to the Lord,</hi> Prov. xvii. 15. Conſidering alſo that excellent Obſervation of a worthy Author, That In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency hath the neareſt Reſemblance of God; and therefore to injure Innocence, is more-eſpecially to injure God himſelf.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:64239:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
